Finding Aid for the Anderson School of Management. UCLA Anderson Forecast. Administrative files and publications. 1952-2012. UARC.0806
UCLA Library Special Collections
Anderson School of Management. UCLA Anderson Forecast. Administrative files and publications.
1952-2012
UCLA Library Special Collections
UARC.0806
10 linear feet (10 cartons)
Record Series 806 documents the creation and evolution of the UCLA [Anderson] Business Forecast, begun in 1952. Records include published copies of each Forecast (national, state, regional, and world), copies of all Proceedings, administrative notes for the annual and quarterly conferences, photographs of participants, and an interview with Robert M. Williams, founder of the Forecast, from 1976.
Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
These records were transferred from the UCLA Anderson School of Management in December 2013.
Directors of the UCLA/Anderson Business Forecasting Project
1952-1981: Robert M. Williams (Retired June 1981)
1981-1990: Larry J. Kimbell (September 1981-June 1990, then a 2-year sabbatical)
1990-1993: David Hensley (September 1990 Acting Director; June 1991 - June 1993 Director)
1993-1997: Larry J. Kimbell (September 1993 - September 1997
1997-1999: Larry J. Kimbell and Daniel J.B.Mitchell, Co-Directors. (December 1997 - 1999. Kimbell retired June 1999)
1999-2000: Daniel J.B. Mitchell (September 1999 - June 2000)
2000-present: Edward E. leamer (September 2000 - present)
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9997173385506533
Forecast Timeline
Missing Title
1952 Robert M. Williams holds the first annual meeting (not public) and releases the first consensus forecast for the nation, for 1953.
1960 First annual and public Forecast Conference
1963, December 12 Forecasting Conference: first forecast of Southern California business conditions
1963-1964 Regional Business Forecasting Project established
1968 Donald Ratacjzak joins Forecast to create econometric models and transition away from consensus (faculty) forecasts
1969, September First UCLA Business Forecasting Seminar (quarterly). Also marks the beginning of the use of econometric models to forecast.
1968, November Mentioned the use of surveys to gather data for the forecast, transitioning away from faculty analyses.
1970, March 25 First mention of a UCLA econometric forecasting model
1971 Forecast begins releasing quarterly forecasts
1971, March Publication of "Proceedings" of conferences, containing forecasts from the UCLA Econometric Models for "the Nation, California, and Southern California"
1973, June Larry J. Kimbell replaced Donald Ratajczak
1973, April 9-10 First International Business Forecasting Conference
1976, January 8-9 First "World Economic Outlook" Conference
1978 Larry J. Kimbell pioneers effort away from mainframe technology to forecasting on personal computers, as the first Forecast on PC is released
1997 The Business Forecasting Center was renamed the UCLA Anderson Business Forecasting Project, and the quarterly publication was renamed the UCLA Anderson Forecast
1998 The UCLA Anderson Forecasting Project was renamed the UCLA Anderson Forecast, aligning with the UCLA Anderson Forecast [publication]
Scope and Content
Record Series 806 contains records and publications of the UCLA Anderson Business Forecast, an economic analysis of national conditions first presented for the year 1953. As the Forecast evolved, it focused on local analyses as well as national predictions, then later offered world-wide outlooks.
The UCLA Business Forecast was one of the first to accurately analyze business and political conditions to predict the near future of employment and business growth. The Business Forecast Project pioneered the use of econometrics and computer models for analysis, rather than the opinions of faculty or other experts.
The first printed Forecast was in 1958. Printed regional Forecasts ceased in 2012, replaced by electronic versions only. This collection includes each printed Forecast, but does not include the later electronic editions.
In addition to official Forecasts and related notes, contents include an interview of Robert M. Williams by Edward V. Sedgwick (ASM faculty/lecturer 1969-1980, Visiting Lecturer 1980-1988). Interview materials include the original audio cassettes and typed transcriptions, as well as Historical Data 1952-1968 [v. 1], a Chronology [v. 3], and notes by the interviewer [v.3].
Administrative files include data and research used in the Business Forecasting Project and UCLA/Anderson Business Forecasts, but not directly linked to specific quarterly seminars/conferences.
The collection also includes Chronological files compiled by Robert M. Williams: data and research used in Business Forecasting Project and UCLA/Anderson Business Forecasts, but not directly linked to specific seminars/conferences. Also included are speeches, presentations, and writings by Robert M. Williams, Donald Ratajczak, Larry J. Kimbell and others, as well as works in which any of these assisted or referenced.
This is an inactive record series; additional University records are not expected to be added.
Arrangement
The records in this collection have been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Official Forecasts (1958-2012)
Series 2: Forecast Proceedings (1961-1988)
Series 3: Forecasts Conferences and Seminars (1952-2012)
Series 4: Administrative files (1960-1990)
Series 5: Past Presentations
Series 6: Robert M. Williams Chronological Files (1950-1986)
- Official Forecasts, Series 1:
  - UCLA Business Forecast., 1958-1987, 1991-1992. (Box 1)
  - UCLA Business Forecast., 1987-1997. (Box 2)
    Scope and Content
    Does not include 1991-Jan. 1993.
  - UCLA Business Forecast. Includes California Regional Outlook September 1998., 1998 March-2006. (Box 3)
  - UCLA Business Forecast. (December 2012 was the final Forecast printed version. Ensuing Forecasts have been electronic only.), 2007 March-2012. (Box 4)
    Biography/History
    December 2012 was the final Forecast printed version. Ensuing Forecasts have been electronic only.
  - Forecast Conference Presentations (quarterly) [CDs]. [Complete set]., 1996 June-1998 September.; (5 envelopes) (Box 5)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
  - Orange County Economic Outlook [annual publication] [Complete set]., 2003 November-2011 November. (Box 4)
  - San Diego Economic Outlook [annual publication] [Complete set]., 2006 May-2011 October. (Box 4)
  - Projections of Economic Activity in California and Southern California to the Year 2000., 1970 October. (Box 1)
  - The UCLA Anderson Forecast: California Regional Forecast., 1998 September. (Box 4)
  - Economic Trends in Major California Metropolitan Areas., 1983 November. (Box 4)
  - Solutions for Our City: April 2, 2007 Conference., 2007 April. (Box 4)
  - Solutions for Our State: March 2008 Economic Outlook for California., 2008 March. (Box 4)
- Proceedings [including published Forecast for the Nation, California/Southern California, additional conference materials, and previous year evaluation]., Series 2:
  - Proceedings of UCLA Business Forecast., 1961-1988. (Box 5)
  - Proceedings of The World Economic Outlook for 1976., 1976 January. (Box 5)
- Forecast Conferences., Series 3:
  - UCLA Business Forecast Conference Records., 1952-1977 March 10.; (61 folders) (Box 6)
  - UCLA Business Forecast Conference Records. From Dec. 1980 to Dec. 2012, only Conference programs and brochures were retained [with some exceptions, see General Note]., 1977 June-2012 December.; (30 folders) (Box 7)
    From Dec. 1980 to Dec. 2012, only Conference programs and brochures were retained [with some exceptions].
- Administrative Files., Series 4:
  - Photographs: Individuals affiliated with UCLA and UCLA Anderson Forecast., 1960-1990. (Box 7)
  - Photographs: Individuals not affiliated with UCLA (or unknown) but affiliated with UCLA Anderson Forecast., 1960-1990. (Box 7)
  - History of the Business Forecasting Project and Seminars., 1963-1973. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence to Columnists re: The UCLA Forecast., 1978. (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, Misc., 1986-1989. (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Administrative Records., 1972. (Box 10)
  - UCLA Five-County Model., 1989. (Box 10)
  - U.S and California Model Flow Charts., 1980-1990. (Box 10)
  - Support for Business Forecasting Project., 1985. (Box 10)
  - General Electric Contract., 1976-1977. (Box 10)
  - Saxon's Office [David Saxon, University of California President]., 1979-1980. (Box 10)
  - Stockman [David] Article and Discussion., 1981. (Box 10)
  - Report to [Assistant Chair] Barber., 1979. (Box 10)
  - Alumni Award to Robert M. Williams, and related material., 1981. (Box 10)
  - UCLA Forecast - Evaluations., 1964-1979. (Box 10)
  - UCLA Business Forecast: Audio recording [CD] from KPPC [NPR radio] "Talk of the City" program., 2003 September 24. (Box 10)
  - UCLA Business Forecast: Historical Data (contents of binder, referenced in 1976 taped interview in this collection). Includes tallies of faculty forecasts, original typed Forecast., 1952-1968.; (2 folders) (Box 10)
    Contents of binder, referenced in 1976 taped interview in this collection. Includes tallies of faculty forecasts, original typed Forecast.
  - Interview of Robert M. Williams by Edward V. Sedgwick., 1976 June 28, 1976 July 13.; (4 folders) (Box 10)
    Edward V. Sedgwick, AGSM faculty/lecturer 1969-1980, and a Visiting Lecturer from 1980 until 1988 retirement. The interview was transcribed as v. 2 of three loose-leaf binders: Contents include the three original audio cassettes, a typed transcription directly from the recordings, and an annotated transcription of the recording.
  - Business Forecast Chronology, and EVS [Edward V. Sedgwick] Notes., 1983. (Box 4)
    Includes page of "Forecast Winners" 1953-1966. Volume 3 of the Robert M. Williams 1976 interview, referenced in the interview.
- Past Presentations., Series 5:
  - Past Presentations., 1979-1994. (Box 10)
  - California Dept. of Finance (Pauline Sweezey)., 1985-1990. (Box 10)
  - Presentation to Jacob Marshak Interdisciplinary Colloquium on Mathematics in the Behavioral Sciences., 1977 October. (Box 10)
  - Speeches - Current., 1972-1980. (Box 10)
  - "Wall St. Week" Luncheon at UCLA Faculty Center., 1987 October. (Box 10)
  - List of Previous Forecast Speakers (Partial), Speaker Forms/Notes., 1983-1990. (Box 10)
- Robert M. Williams Chronological Files., Series 6:
  - Writings, Speeches, Presentations of Robert M. Williams., 1950-1959.; (2 folders) (Box 8)
  - Original Artwork for Regional Reports., Circa 1954. (Box 8)
    Includes prints and 35mm negatives.
  - Rents, CPI, Vacancy Rates., Circa 1954. (Box 8)
  - Writings, Speeches, Presentations., 1960-1969. (Box 8)
  - Capital Stock Estimates., 1965. (Box 8)
  - Quantitative Methods of Business Forecasting (UCLA Extension Course, co-taught by Dr. Williams)., 1966 September 26-27. (Box 8)
  - Diagrams and 1967 Forecast, Southern California Model., 1967 Spring. (Box 8)
  - Joint Economic Committee [JEC] Statement by Robert M. Williams., 1969 February 24. (Box 8)
  - Analysis of Forecasts., 1963. (Box 8)
  - Southern California Model., 1963. (Box 8)
  - Business Forecasting: 3-day Conference., 1964 January-October. (Box 8)
  - Economic Time Series Decomposition Program - Notes., 1964 February. (Box 8)
  - Boeing Study: Layoffs subject to Dyna-Soar Cancellation., 1964. (Box 8)
  - Asking Price Index - Tabulations and Correspondence., 1956, 1964. (Box 8)
  - Eight-Region Model., 1970 October. (Box 8)
  - Tables: Ten Counties Data (Case E, F, G, H, I, K), California (Case E, F, K)., 1970 October. (Box 8)
  - Projections of Economic Activity in California and Southern California to the Year 2000., 1970 October. (Box 8)
  - A Long-Run Model of California Economic Activity., 1970 October. (Box 8)
  - Writings, Speeches, Presentations., 1970-1977. (Box 8)
  - A Quarterly Economic Model for California, by Donald Ratajczak., Circa 1971. (Box 8)
  - Kentucky Model., 1971. (Box 8)
  - Miami Paper., 1971 November. (Box 8)
  - Interpretation of UCLA California Model - 1971 Version. (Box 8)
  - Charts & Tables: Housing & Construction in Southern Calif. 1960-1973. Construction & Real Estate Activity 1959-1980., 1972 December. (Box 8)
  - California Forecast to the Year 2000., 1972 March. (Box 8)
  - Economic Impact of California Withholding, by Donald Ratajczak., 1972 Fall. (Box 8)
  - Tables: Forecast of California Economic Activity: Projections to Year 2000; The Most Probable Case., 1972 May, August. (Box 8)
  - UCLA Business Forecast: overview., 1968 August, 1976 November. (Box 8)
  - Data Resources Inc: Meeting and Report., 1972 December 02. (Box 8)
  - Writings, Speeches, Presentations., 1973. (Box 8)
  - Equations for the UCLA Financial and Housing Model., 1973 July. (Box 8)
  - Don's National Model - Process Described., 1973 May-June. (Box 8)
  - Tables: SMSAs [Standard Metropolitan Statistical Areas] and non-SMSA Counties in Selected Years 1950-1971., 1973 August. (Box 8)
  - An Econometric Model of the Greater Los Angeles Five County Region, by A. William Gindra., 1974. (Box 8)
  - The UCLA Econometric Model of California, by Larry J. Kimbell., 1974 March. (Box 8)
  - California Model and Database., 1975. (Box 8)
  - UCLA Econometric Model of California., 1975 February. (Box 8)
  - Map: California SMSAs [Standard Metropolitan Statistical Areas]., 1975 July 01. (Box 8)
  - New York City Crisis., 1975 June-October. (Box 8)
  - Looking Ahead with Pacific Telephone., 1976 April. (Box 8)
  - Glossary of the Variable Names used in the UCLA Econometric Model of California., 1976 November. (Box 8)
  - Final Report on Long Range Forecasting Methodology for the California Dept. of Transportation., 1976 April. (Box 8)
  - Equations- UCLA United States Model., 1977. (Box 8)
  - UCLA Regional Model of California., 1977. (Box 8)
  - Five County Region - Forecast for Los Angeles and California., 1977 March-June. (Box 8)
  - Impact of Loss of Jobs due to B-1 Bomber Cancellation., 1977 [April]. (Box 8)
  - Northrup Analysis - Impact of Additional Jobs on Employment, Incomes, and Gross Product in the Los Angeles Area, California, and the U.S.: A Report for the Northrup Corporation, by Larry J. Kimbell and Robert M. Williams., 1977 April. (Box 8)
  - The UCLA Econometric Forecasting System. By Larry J. Kimbell, presented to Western Economic Association., 1977 June 20-23. (Box 8)
  - Writings, Speeches, Presentations., 1977 March-December. (Box 8)
  - The UCLA Econometric Forecasting System, presented by Larry J. Kimbell at the Western Econometric Assn 52nd Annual conference., 1977 June 20-23. (Box 8)
  - UCLA Business Forecast: State of California Meeting; Urban Development Strategy Impact Techniques and Illustrative Simulations, by Larry J. Kimbell., 1977 December 9. (Box 8)
  - Board of Visitors Materials., 1977 December 14. (Box 8)
  - UCLA Long-Run Projections for California and 17 California SMSAs., 1977-1980. (Box 9)
  - Table: SMSA Growth in 17 California Metropolitan Areas in 1976., 1978. (Box 9)
  - Total Personal Income in SMSAs Counties and Individual Cities in Selected Years., 1978 July. (Box 9)
  - Differential Unemployment Rates - California and United States., 1978. (Box 9)
  - Proposition 13: Research Conference., 1978 July 13-14. (Box 9)
  - Proposition 13: Writings, Speeches, Meetings; authors affiliated with UCLA., 1978-1979. (Box 9)
  - Proposition 13: Survey., 1978 June 14. (Box 9)
  - Proposition 13: Pre-passage subject files related to research., 1975-1978. (Box 9)
  - Proposition 13: Post-passage Writings, Speeches., 1978 June-September. (Box 9)
  - Proposition 13: Post-passage subjects related to research., 1978 June-1982 June.; (6 folders) (Box 9)
  - Writings, Speeches, Presentations not related to Proposition 13., 1978. (Box 9)
  - Research Conference on Proposition 13., 1978 November. (Box 9)
  - Table 8: Population, Personal Income and Retail Sales in 17 Metropolitan Areas of California in 1976. Map - SMSA areas., 1978 November. (Box 9)
  - Saxon [David Saxon, U.C. President] Jarvis II; Proposition 9., 1979-1980. (Box 9)
  - California Model: Dept. of Finance [State of California]., 1979 March. (Box 9)
  - California Projections., 1980 February 15. (Box 9)
  - UCLA Quarterly Forecasting Model., 1980 April 1. (Box 9)
  - Writings, Speeches, Presentations., 1980. (Box 9)
  - An Econometric Model of Final Demand Components of California, by Larry J. Kimbell and Peter Jaquette. Presented to the Air Resources Board, State of California. Growth in California: Prospects and Consequences, by Larry J. Kimbell and David Shulman., 1980 November, 1981 August. (Box 9)
  - Writings, Speeches, Presentations., 1983. (Box 9)
  - Writings, Speeches, Presentations., 1984. (Box 9)
  - FermiLab [Superconducting Super Collider]: Research and Studies., [1984]-1986. (Box 9)
  - Economic Impact of Superconducting Super Collider [SSC] in California., 1986 November. (Box 9)
  - Index cards from card file of Robert M. Williams., 1950-1960. (Box 10)
  - Business contact cards from the Rolodex of Robert M. Williams., 1950-1960. (Box 10)